I heard you talking the other day that's
some sorry
it must be the round rebirth at
real-time image
so what do you say that is you can you
mention it was the translation was
something like wandering fun yeah
roaming roaming on some sir Artie
if I remember correctly just means throw
me just keep roaming on and all
now here than elsewhere
no the whole idea of like around rebirth
it's a it's a notion that people develop
based on this life and based on on the
like self-centeredness of this life by
that I mean they use this life as a
reference point and from there you kind
of die
but actually fundamentally if you look
at the experience from the point of view
the five aggregates there are no rounds
is just the rising and passing away of
the very same thing so any rebirth that
you might have it's within the five
aggregates so then so that's why it's
not even accurate to say is the five
aggregates that get reborn because they
would they would kind of imply four by
five aggregates traveling from one but
there is no travel from one birth to the
other rebirth is within the five
aggregates as in reappearance
reemergence it's within the five
aggregates that you have and can know
right here right now that's why if
somebody fully understands the nature of
panchik under they they fully understood
the nature of rebirth the nature of
reappearance that's why the Buddha said
it's if somebody if somebody remembers
the previous previous life one previous
life for five days five hundred years
ago the lifetimes all they're going to
remember is the five aggregates or one
among them so that that samsara is the
five aggregates your experience as a
whole it's the container of the samsara
within that your point of view your
immediacy the content of your senses
that can be different depending on the
river it can be more refined it can be
it can be closer it can be Pleasant it
can be torturous but overall in its
nature the father gets there that's it
so in a way there is no like coming and
going and cycling around the realm of
know the whole world all of the realms
all the possible realms of Uri but are
within the five elements that you have
right here and now
so they said the notion of RIBA it's
it's more accurately sort of reflect
upon from the point of view of like a
change of rebirth would be change of
immediacy change of the degree of
immediacy of your senses the nature of
your sensors but in terms of the nature
of things in nature phenomena and edge
of things to appear so that's why that's
why it whenever they would talk about
the rebirth in the suit is it would be
only like in the sense it's almost like
a like a memory like you remember what
you done yesterday
you remember to then ten days ago you
remember what you done ten years ago and
then yeah some people might remember
what they've done ten lifetimes ago but
it's still the same that same container
of their experience the same nature the
fire it's almost the same point of view
in a way so the notion of you traveling
from one rebirth to the others it's a
notion based on the projection of the
external world external point of view
independent of your experience as a
whole and that's that's that's that's a
fellow so you can't even conceive things
in such a purely impersonal manner
because they will require you to
generally step outside of yourself
outside of the container of your five
aggregates outside of your point of view
and thinking something outside of your
point of view it's inconceivable because
whatever you can conceive it's within
your point of view from the with point
of view who rises well the point changes
I suppose you want the degree of point
of view can change within the within the
container of the five aggregates
like for example with the animals being
being the lower realms means their point
of view their capacities of reflection
are more forcefully absorbed with the
content of the senses so that's why they
can't step back and become aware of
their situation or they can do it or
very little degrees mostly is just
absorption with immediacy hunger hunger
fear fear play play running chasing
Fighting's they can't just wait a minute
why am i doing this they don't have that
much space in that deflection and a
point of view it's too absorbed but it's
still the point of view that's why
somebody can remember the previous
lifetimes cuz it's through these through
this container of the five aggregates
that generates this point of view you
can actually remember more so a life
doesn't last long
well you know in a way that's true but
the problem is again even when people
think about the notion of time they
think in this external scientific
impersonal sense and that's
inconceivable as in things are in time
so they can say the life lost this much
and by the point of view lost forever
that's why the that's with the notion
any notion of eternity in a sense of
permanence it's it's wrong because it's
founded in the wrong view and the wrong
view is that which contradicts the
nature of the phenomena the way they
appear you can't step outside of the
five agrees you assuming the world
outside of the five aggregates means
you're basically having the wrong
assumption in regards to the nature so
you could truly say that if you want to
be accurate you can't say that of five
aggregates lasts for long because that
would imply that there in time while in
reality your notion of time is already
within that container of the five agree
your experience as a whole so then more
accurately you would say that
Bava grades are not in time five agree
it's an off time as in your notion of
duration is already on the basis of
enduring five aggregates well yes not so
strictly speaking you can say yeah it
lasts it lasts infinitely but not
eternally
there's many different points of you
like I have a point of view now yes well
again they would never assume the
external point of view they could then
compare all these different points of
view no you have your point of view
there is that's it that's all you can
know now you can come close to my point
of view but you can't have my point of
view because that would require you
becoming me as an individual well there
is internal point of view the one that
you know for yourself and then you can
see other point other points of view
such as external points of view so you
can say there are points with you but
you can't see them at the same level but
you can't even compare them to the same
level because they were required to step
outside your point of view that you're
inseparable from and then
what about development tools developer
evolution theory of evolution sir I will
continue means all people
naturally what what evolves is not a
point of view it's the well what can be
said to evolve or proliferate anyhow you
wanna call it is senses and the world
around the immediacy around the content
of your experience but at the point of
view is modern level of how you regard
that how you see it how much you allow
it to control you to absorb is to
deprive you of your own capacity of your
own actual reflection so in that sense
point of view can it's pretty much well
it's it's indirectly affected by
proliferation and evolution as in it
always he always maintained potential
stepping back and reflecting upon the
immediacy of your current
to reserve with these realms the animal
realm
and getting between let's come here is
the realms in between Nets I think it
goes uh-huh but there is no stepping
there's no halfway round alright well
there's no crossing between the realms
for sure the missing link no because
again any any notion of comparison
connection would require an external
point of view point of view that it's
independent of yourself of your five
aggregates of your experience as a whole
and that's inconceivable so all you know
fandom logically speaking is what you
have as in a based on that you can then
infer that the immediacy in the senses
and the sense engagement can be
different as in it can it can exercise a
different extent a different amount of
force over you like for animals the
senses exercised way too much force for
the reflection to be able to maintain
itself as much as a human can do but
there is no crossing like there is the
animal realm that sits here then there
is the human realm that sits here and
then the being goes into animal realm
and then it kind of floats from animal
into human or something like that
that's like an externally projected
notion of some sort of cosmology I mean
if you're talking about it there is no
other way to talk about it then in these
external terms but those designations
should not be misunderstood when it
comes to your point of view you can only
see it from the inside and that's how
that's how that's how the Buddha would
refer that like an arahant or somebody
who is fully understood understood the
samsara not by traveling in previous
lives are waiting for the future lives
no you understood the content he
understood the actually not the content
the container the basis on account of
any different content can manifest
itself and by saying different content
means different birth
content of an enema content of an animal
realm or content of the Deverell as in
the refinement of the complement content
the type of engagement of the content
that's basically what I you can refer to
as a earth realm
so you don't necessarily develop each
but you're not getting better
oh no not sure come here
you're getting kind of worse better well
based on your actions then you kind of
play the part into what kind of content
you're going to be your point of view
will be paired with later on in the same
sense again you can you don't have to
think about previous life and future
life it's the principle that you can
extend but you can think within this
life if the actions you're making now
quite unwholesome harming a lot of
people for example causing lots of
damage you can safely assume that your
whole life is heading that direction so
then in five six years when the whole
world is against you they're trying to
imprison you they chase you because of
the crimes you committed your content
has been significantly changed to like
like more pressing more enduring more
unpleasant because of your actions
they've been affecting in that manner if
if if your actions are in this very life
are actually not harming anybody are
helpful to ever then yeah that that's
going to be influencing your environment
the most not 100% so there many other
many other factors they can many other
factors that can play the part but to a
great deal if a person doesn't go around
committing crimes they don't have to
worry about where anybody's going to get
them catch them their excesses revenge
on them but those who do that becomes
your daily environment that becomes your
daily content of the phenomena that
keeps appearing for the point of view of
the further actions you do on account of
it so you could then see if you carry on
that kind of behavior for years it's not
it's not a big stretch to assume that oh
yeah so when this life sort of breaks
apart with this body breaks apart the
content is gonna realize it's just going
to carry on further in the same
direction because that's how you've been
exercising your point of view and your
actions and your
there's no like a natural end to some
sorry we just get better they'll evolve
in a good well in a way it's again it's
not like that you reenter some solid
beauty you are this samsara the five
aggregates affected by ignorant is what
samsara is this this experience of the
five hundreds for somebody who is not
enlightened that's that's already what
samsara is which means this experience
you just gonna stay infinitely unless a
person freeze this very experience from
that ignorant then it will not be appear
the content will not well you won't be
paired with any content with any form
that point of view will not be paired
it'll just go extinct as the Buddha will
describe the barniz extinction
anywhere else it well it doesn't go
anywhere else that will require you to
jump from a point in space to a point B
in space which then assumes external
point of view of space which is only can
be based on the five areas right here
right now so that's why your experience
is not in space and in time it's off
space and off time you get the notion of
space based on your perceptions and
notion of time pretty much based on your
feelings and their endurance so it's
secondary to it
so if you stop thinking in terms of
arming space and time
then the whole notion of rebirth becomes
much more intelligible and it just fits
perfectly with pretty much everything
else that you can know right here and
right now
point of view is beyond time it's off
time let's not be on time because again
that assumes time and now something
beyond notion of time it's basically
result at the point of view in space
notion time in space news after the five
aggregates so in a way like again you
can think it's on the level of this life
so say you have used today's a new day
you do you do certain things you do
certain things and so on then you go to
sleep then you wake up then again it's a
new day you do things but okay you have
a memory of yesterday and so on they
will affect your choice today you have
assumption of tomorrow it's going to
affect your choice today and so on but
it's all within your experience that's
all within your point of view within the
five agree you wouldn't be asking
yourself off was it me from yesterday
the same who became the one today it's
gonna be the one tomorrow no it's just
me who went to sleep yesterday and now I
woke up and you know what it's a new day
from a reference point of view of
yesterday as it from a memory but all of
that is within this experience today so
you can extend yesterday 10 years ago 10
lifetimes ago
you've just been waking up in different
environments so to speak so that's what
of what does what the question of who
gets rebirth is a wrong question because
it assumes this external floating from
one life to another and what is it that
it changes and goes this that's what the
Buddha wouldn't even answer it because
it's based on a completely wrong premise
of this external world point of view
that it's kind of independent of you but
you can't possibly conceive anything
like that because if something if you
consider something dependent of you can
only do so on account of depending upon
your experience with the varieties which
means it's not
and it was really wrong with you and
send a question that will come out of it
as in who gets reborn from life number
one to alive number two he just requires
this this non-existent external world
independent of your experience
independent of your sense of being any
point of view
so that's why yeah just ask yourself
yourself that you can remember from ten
years ago
who's that how did that person from 10
years ago become youth today and you
know that's well it's not really a right
question two formulas like that how did
it because you would assume that
something has kind of traveled
independent of you from a point of view
in the past to a point of view right
here but no it's just no it's just this
point of this experience has been
enduring for 10 years there have been
changes on a particular level while
overall it was remaining the same
container the same nature of perception
you've been having different perceptions
different intentions you've been
performing different actions ten years
ago could you have different values and
different views but overall it was still
the nature perception the nature feeling
the nature of intention the nature of
the views and that's within this and you
know you can't step outside of that
Adama doesn't step outside of it
he actually realizes that outside is
inconceivable so he stops conceiving it
and by doing so he removes ignorance in
regard to the inside of himself in
regards to the nature of perception
feeling intention the nature of the
viewers and that's how he extinguishes
that container it ceases to be the
fertile ground for this maintenance of
the beam because it assumed
no no that's well in a sort of honor
stops assuming that like the fundamental
the core of the the external assumption
of your own experience is after bad
external sense and yourself pretty much
independent of this experience in it
that's why they would ask who gets
reborn because they assume the
impersonal world is personal space and
time from which things just flow from
one birth to the other realm to distress
but no matter the realm the nature of
the fire gates is the same which means
also if you want to find how it is in
more subtle realms course around you can
do so on a kind of understanding the
nature of this experience that you have
cuz it's within it that's what and
that's why it's called roaming omelet
it's just this experience just keeps
perpetuating itself on and on and on and
the but again he did give a simulator
the illustrates that he said it's like a
man leaving his home village and goes to
next village and from their village he
goes to next village and from that
village he goes to next village and then
it's xx village they asked him where did
you come from and he says well before
this village I was in this village
before that I was in another village in
another village in another village so
yeah if you were to describe it to
somebody else it would sound like that
external manner but from his point of
view he was always in the village that
he was in he couldn't step outside of
himself and then explain to himself how
oh he didn't need you how he from one
village cross to another village no he
was just I was in this village then I
went on to another world but it's still
the same experience each time he was in
different village he had a different
content of a village but in terms of the
nature we expects his experience
perception of the village intentions of
the village feelings in the village were
the same the nature remained the same
the nature of the fire great that's what
the world many said even if you remember
five hundred lifetimes more from before
all you remembering these five
aggregates right here right now or one
among them
you cannot you cannot know the five
aggregates directly or humans well you
cannot examine them and take them apart
again because that would require the
external point of view in regards to
them you can only see the insides of the
five aggregates and when you think oh
this is the inside you already start
implying the assumption become
conceiving of the outside
that's what would a man he conceives in
matter from it apart from Etta he
conceives matter his mind he conceived
and then he goes on in that Mullaperiyar
suta for all the other aggregates in all
the other ways by implicitly perceiving
it as ah this is the inside you
automatically assume the outside to an
extent so you just have to undo that
implicit conceiving and then the
assumption the outside will fade
and you again you undo that in place in
conceiving not on account of finding out
the external view of the five aggregates
and then examining it one by one that's
inconceivable that's impossible you can
do it by stop regarding it is mine
right here right now by saying that it's
independent of you by seeing that it's
subjected to destruction being obsessive
did it seem accessible because if you
were truly able to access it they
control it it would obey you
you listening well exactly like like
some people some Minds can go to the
subtle level of being mindful of the
earth element but whether you are
mindful of the earth element whether
you're mindful of the bodies seated on
this chair it's it's the same principle
that's why you can arrive at the same
goal without needing to refine it to the
point of the earth element
being mindful of your experience as a
whole band up with this body with this
phone without overdoing your thoughts
into assuming the external world point
of view but without becoming negligent
in regards to your own absorption with
your own senses
so again if a person wants to reflect
along these lines they can within this
with with experience in the memories of
this slide same if I ask you where were
you I don't know five days ago Utah was
there where were you 10 years ago I was
there so in a way yeah there was some
change but within your point of view
hasn't changed your views might have
changed but the direction of you having
views the experiences are hold the
nature of perception the nature the
nature of body the form the nature
person feeling the nature perception the
nature of intentions and nature of
consciousness that hasn't changed that
container has remained unchanged since
you can remember and that's the thing so
I remember since when you were two years
old and that's kind of where it stopped
by the only stops because your memory
stops there but the principle carries on
which means then yes some people can
then start remembering more but it's
still within the same principle off of
the memory that you know so that's why
in that sense it's not correct to say
that it's all yet it's it's my sense of
self they go reborn or if it was
previously in this life now it's in this
life and it will go in another life no
it's not in space and time
where does memory says well it's it's
that that that infinity of change on a
more particular level within the
container that stays the same the
container of your experience as a whole
the container of the file access the
container of your point of view
that's why memories in a way endless
sorry beginningless because there was no
first beginning before which didn't
exist and then you became as the Buddha
said a visa has no first point when it
manifests it shouldn't be there but it
is there and it's been there is
beginningless that's why once you undo
it cannot realize cannot reappear can
order emerge because he was never meant
to be there the ignorance that the
assumption of the external point of view
all of that was not meant to read it it
doesn't fit there the oppo done is not
the five aggregates cannot be the fire
gates cannot become the five aggregates
cannot enter the five aggregates but
cannot be found apart from them so
desire and lust which is another way of
saying misconceiving
the five agreed do putana the
assumptions are there in regard to it
you stop misconceiving it the open
anaphase
and say this exactly there is no more
being bound with the content like this
then like that then another one then
another one
so that what generates some size is
what generates maybe know the right word
what keeps it good yeah what maintains
samsara don't if you don't have bigger
in samsara cannot be maintained to thank
you it's mental again said where does it
sit implies placement in space oh it's
over here
but that assumes the external point of
view where you can place it like a box
on a shelf or something in space at most
X does be a figure of speech but if the
figure of speech is taken literally
literally as in then you start assuming
that since the space in the brain yeah
it's in the brain it's in the center or
some molecules there or something it's
not more in your brain that it's in with
more in your toes in the same sense
consciousness is not in your body it's
paired with the body it's in regard to
the body but see any notions that you
have on account any notions that you
have of your body it's on the basis of
conscious body any notions that you have
on the kind of cop any notions you have
in regard to consciousness it's on the
basis of the conscious body conscious
body is the basis then you cannot step
outside of nor separate and investigate
separately that's what whenever you look
at the body you're conscious whenever
you're trying to discern consciousness
the necessary living body needs to be
there but the problem is when people
look at either body of consciousness and
then develop the view it places them
underneath or ladder as more fundamental
than the diet of conscious body that you
have right here right now but you can't
step outside of it so then you have to
realize that no no doesn't matter how
pleasing the the notions of the body you
might develop and the theories and the
views that can only be done within the
container of conscious body you cannot
step outside of that so a scientific
view it's inherently wrong not wrong in
terms of the contents but wrong in terms
of the nature that's why you cannot use
science to arrive and explain the nature
of being the nature experience the
nature of feelings for that matter
that's what whenever the scientists
tried to talk about feelings and
describe feelings they end up describing
perceptions of sensations in the body
but perception is perception and feeling
is feeling you can't feel your
perceptions so perceptions and feelings
in the same sense like body and
consciousness they are paired but
they're independent of each other but
they're inseparable from each other and
the Buddha said that you can't set
perception feeling and intentions
conjoined you cannot take them apart and
examine them separate from the other two
means that's the basis that you cannot
conceive different in any other shape or
form and any conceive is you have it
within that container of those vases
hence if you're conceiving that
contradict in the basis it's wrong here
that's why it's wrong here
so that's why if you were to have a
scientific view in terms of practicing
Adama it's a wrong view because it
contradicts the nature of the basis on
account of which you developed the
scientific view that external world that
you cannot actually conceive truly you
cannot access in that impersonal manner
as as the science leads you to believe
because you always have a point of view
and the notion of no this is beyond the
point of view is within your point of
view oh this is external to my point of
view well you can only see that to your
point of view which means it's not
external the true external well see you
can't even designate correctly if you
say the true external well it's not
external then because you're talking
about it you're designating something
and if there is something even an
ambiguous notion of external world it's
within this container of the five agree
thus it's not truly external that's why
there is no real matter a real reality
behind these appearances or anything
like that what appears that's what's
real
so right like I should speak about God
our God is like the show inconceivable
sure but you are conceiving it through
through labeling it through designated
it how it's inconceivable you cannot
express the deity the eternal well you
just expressed it by saying it's not
expressible no matter what you express
so that you realize you can't step
outside it's obvious of the experience
as a whole and there was never the point
that's why you stop looking for some
hidden transcendental realities which is
we usually think well usually people
think are a hunch your base no realize
you can't you only have to be stopped
conceiving that there is outside to be
found because conceiving the outside is
conceiving the independence of this
experience as a whole and that's a
definition of art of other an
independent center self independent of
the five aggregates independent of the
form feeling in perceptions intentions
in consciousness yet any notion of that
independence is based on this form
feeling perception intentions
consciousness thus it's actually
secondary to it thus it cannot be
independent so that's all a person needs
to do stop assuming the external stop
assuming that master self
stop conceiving it as possible
and that's Mullaperiyar suit in a
nutshell the very first suit America
you'll give it before anything there was
nothing exactly
exactly
well that's something cuz you're
thinking of it so if something is truly
nothing then you can't even designate it
as nothing as absence of something is
just inconceivable to us you can't even
think it and let alone designate a
something so if you keep trying to think
it and you just keep trying to inflict
yourself you don't experience it well
you should realize that it's unthinkable
and the projection towards thinking it
you realize well that's already
thinkable within this thus it cannot
stand for that which is truly
unthinkable so when the thought of
unthinkable stops conceiving something
that it's thinkable that's when a
thought recognizes its own extent
some philosophers speak about being yes
yes but the ones that do ended up
assuming the external world from which
they very plausibly defined being
anything but that's already then
contradicting the basic phenomena
principle that they used to rival yeah
he can have the experience of absence of
greed aversion delusion but he can have
it
affected by the assumption of external
sense of self external master external
point of view that is external
scientific order thus that experience of
of not self that experience of freedom
from greed over delusion is appropriated
by that fully gratuitous views
thus he conceives that Nibbana he
conceives in it he conceives apart from
it
he conceives in his mind and thus he
cannot study his mind well because of
that Danny Banach and not become the
experience that he develops fully
consistently but it isn't any banner because there is
but it isn't any banner because there is
another suit imaginary car later on when
the Buddha gives a similar description
and how person with his conceit think so
I'm at this in the barn I'm attaining
the banners is listening banners mine
and the Buddha said yeah but he refers
to is the actual Nibbana but because of
the self center point of view because of
those assumptions of self mastery he
does not enter
he cannot sustain
it's not a different abundance it's it's
it's a kapa it's like when people try oh
no it's a different advantage just an
easy way to dismiss it but the bullets
himself said although he asserts that
which deadening his namana doesn't undo
it because he can't study his his
experience in it he keeps he keeps miss
consuming end so what you were saying it
don't seem to be the end it's it's it's
the end of the assumptions that you
developed based on the familiarity with
the current content of your experience
so then it's the end of that but it's
it's far from an end of the five
aggregates the true end from being it's
far from the end of being
but yeah most people the entire life the
sense of self the views are based on the
content of this president spirits on
that assumption of the external world
and that whole thing so then yet that
fends all that that's why it's a
frightening
but if you if you yeah if you stop if
you if you removed all the conceiving
that stopped wrongly as humans things in
regard to this content of this
experience this life there is no death
and the deathless that which is death
can apply only way the content with the
assumptions in regard to the content of
your senses exist you remove the
assumptions that is the true deathless
it's just the notion of death is
inconceivable that's almost what a lot
of people think well again with
nothingness see the fact that you can
think that I can have an ocean of
complete nothingness well that's
something that notion is real as such
which means which means it's not the
true nothingness because if it's a true
nothing that you can think it but is non
conceiving not conceiving that means
stop assuming wrong things in regard to
the nature of death that's what not
conceiving death leads newborn yeah you
can have an understanding developed it
without assuming well that's what
development is undoing the assumptions
you can't see well no you can you can
enter it you can step into it so to
speak you can't see the external examine
it because if you are seeing it like
that you miss conceiving it so you can
enter Nibbana by removing all the
assumptions that misconceived on the
balance then your experience
automatically becomes experience of
Nibbana but it's not like you do the
work of removing the assumptions and
then the gates open and then you walk
into deliver now undoing the work
removing all the conceiving is when the
bond is is it missing
in a way you are striving to bring about
the ending be yeah you're not striving
to find as I said some kind of external
transcendental entity that you merge
with or what it saves you know you're
striving to stop misconceiving this very
experience to stop appropriating in his
mind stop entertaining mistaken Garuda's
assumption in regard to it and that will
undo the beat because that's what being
is it's a mistake in regards to things
that appear mistake of ownership mistake
of the sense of self mistake of
permanence some people say that it
sounds like a kind of trying to kill
yourself well if the suicide of
ignorance sure it's the suicide of the
self view but it's not the suicide of
the content on a con account of which
you develop the sense of self that's
like people killing the five are trying
to kill the five aggregates because they
can't get rid of who Perdana in regard
to the bunch of Conda so it's not
knowing where the problem is your
attacking it at the wrong at the wrong
place so that's usually what suicide is
back in the body trying to kill the body
so it will kind of kill you but if you
are done yourself under undone your
sense of self
then you don't care about living or
killing the body because it's not
suicide it's suicide when you're trying to get
it's suicide when you're trying to get
rid of that self sense of self by
destroying the environment that supports
it but if you look at it as the way I
described it you can't destroy the five
aggregates you just keep changing the
content of it through getting a
different birth three different rebirth
which means you then can't you don't you
don't you don't do anything about the
underlying problem of misconceiving the
content that resulted in you having that
self for you in the first place so you
might have annihilated the temporary or
rather the particular content but
overall your mistake in regard to the
nature the content stays the same hence
you keep getting porn on and on and on
again and keep reappropriation things
misappropriating misconceiving and keep
being bound by samsara
so the true suicide the one that can
truly kill that sense of self is the one
that doesn't kill the body doesn't aim
at the body but actually undos undoes
the ignorance in regard to the body in
regard to the phenomenon of the body and
the experience as a whole that removes
the basis completely uproots to send
yourself truly annihilated
that's when ibanez annihilation greed
aversion delusion of conceiving zuv
appropriation of the sense of self but
not annihilation of the content and of
the environment and of the five
aggregates
because it's obviously suicides seem to
be quite bad yeah yeah cause it's it's
justa finda proliferation of already of
the original mistake you misconceive the
content of your experience you're not
seeing the nature which you develop the
sense of ownership and sense of self
external self that's in charge of this
whole thing and then despite being
paired with unpleasant feelings and so
on you still can't see that you are not
in control of those things and instead
of take that as a way of liberating
yourself from that gratuitous assumption
of ownership of control you don't try to
like like destroy the whole thing while
actually aiming it destroying their
ownership and that sense of self but as
I said before as the suitors say EW
piranha the assumption of self or any
other assumption it's not the five
aggregates but it's not to be far found
apart from them you need to discern the
nature of the five aggregates so you
stop having desire and lastly regard to
five aggregates as a result of that the
sense of self that being simultaneously
generally bias ceases but people don't
notice or then they just try to destroy
the problem just dismiss the problem and
that's how you solve the problem so
that's why suicide is bad because on
account of the problem you just
perpetuated a problem but then remove
the possibility of understanding the
problem in any foreseeable future
so what what about people who have
understood the problem the other hands
yeah well their suicide like in the
suitors when our hands come it is it's
not a suicide because they were not
aiming or trying to get rid of that
sense of self they were not obviously
not destroyed nor anything well they as
the Buddha would say he wouldn't use the
word death as like they kill themselves
he would say they would the ones they
were sick physically sick the body was
just it's horrible falling apart State
dysentery and whatnot beyond repair
beyond medicine and they were already
uprooted everything in regard to that
experience so then they just literally
sped up quicken the vet which was
already coming to its end by freeing the
sense of freeing the assumption of the
external world freeing the Sun then
removing the notion appropriation the
body that has still remained for another
hunt the five aggregates are the last
because there is no desire and lust in
regard to it there is no reappearance of
the content anymore once this body
breaks apart it will not carry on
basically that's it this is the true
ending so for another hunted like
venerable China in maha nikaya
who was soil and so sick in constant
discomfort he well he has no reason to
wait whether this body will break apart
in five years or five days because he
done the work of uprooting everything
that's what Morton Seuss sorry there's
nothing what there's nothing more to be
done so then because the circumstances
of dead body were so disagreeable he had
no reason to endure it why would Ian do
nothing to prove nothing to do
so then he's just decided to kill that
body as in just do instead of waiting
for five years for it to disintegrate he
done it in five days
but that's valid thing to do only after
you become an utter heart otherwise if
there is still desire and lust in regard
to that dead body that you are trying to
kill means you are committing a suicide
to various degree obviously depending on
how much desire and lust is a motivator
for that action but for another hand it
can't be any so for him it's truly just
just just just fast like speeding up the
process of the disintegration of the
five are great but if there is desire
and lust in regards it they are not the
scintillating means you do remain bound
with the nature then which means you
will keep reappearing so the reason why
suicide is very unwholesome it's because
by doing it you you end up burning
yourself most likely with even less
fortunate content of your five
aggregates which will then prevent the
possibility of reflection necessary for
removing the assumption and then
developing wisdom and understanding for
example the animal realm so through your
own ignorance greed aversion delusion
and assumptions of wrong assumptions in
the sense of self you committed acts
then that removed even further the
possibility for you understanding that
problem in the first place
and which means then you have to keep
enduring samsara much longer because of
your own ignorant actions so that's why
somebody who is not in our hand it's
actually better not to kill themselves
not to commit suicide and endure it
obviously a lot of people are not even
practicing regattas heavy disease
painful cancel something
and there is no cure yeah a lot of pain
yeah then they choose say euthanasia
sure it kills yourselves because no well
it's it's sure that the time will come
and there is no hope or but it's not
true is that that pain is the greatest
pain that you can explain it because the
mind that it's still affected by
ignorance like the worst pain of the
human realm might not be anything in
comparison to the to the pains of loba
who've been paired with lower types of
content in your future reappearances so
from that point again any reference you
can make it's based of this life and it
seems unbearable but you have actually
no idea which where you are heading so
that's why it's better to try and make
absolutely most of it while you can
because you will die eventually
and the developed mind can endure it
if the mind did not have or is SB
there's been undermining the road it for
a longer time so it couldn't develop to
the same extent but even then there is a
serious amount of responsibility if a
person commits suicide and they still
have the wrong view there's still a
patina they still haven't understood even what
they still haven't understood even what
nature of Nirvana is because because
they might be removing that possibility
of understanding they remove it for a
long long time because if they're if
they're next next birth and rebirth and
reappearances whatever you want to call
it our lower or even if they are higher
it's just infused with divine pleasures
you won't be thinking in the collective
much so that's why you really want to make
so that's why you really want to make
most of this opportunity that you have
where you can reflect with that right
balance which is what human realm is but
if you done their work if you fully
freed the whole experience of the Father
there's no external assumptions no
conceiving there is no suicide there is
no murder there is no death there is
something that everyone should be
training towards because everyone is
going some somewhere yeah ultimately
that should be that's pretty much the
sole the aim of any being in any realm
should be freeing themselves from being
bound with that with the content of
their experience because I'm sorry I
just attempted enduring pain
yeah that's like the beginning of
restraint as well like while you're
healthy you start practicing that
because when the senses start falling
apart if you practice restraint and
enduring you won't be able to whoa